John K. Terres Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
John K. Terres Papers.
undated, 1901-1989.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Terres, John Kenneth.
2.5 linear feet.
Terres was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on 17 December 1905. He attended the State Teachers College (Indiana, PA), Cornell University and New York University. A field biologist for the Soil Conservation Service from 1936 until 1942, Terres authored, co-authored and edited more than fifty books pertaining to natural history.
MSS19980287
Biography
Terres was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on 17 December 1905. He attended the State Teachers College (Indiana, PA), Cornell University and New York University. A field biologist for the Soil Conservation Service from 1936 until 1942, Terres authored, co-authored and edited more than fifty books pertaining to natural history. Among the most outstanding of his publications are the award-winning From Laurel Hill to Siler's Hog (John Burroughs Medal, 1971), Song Birds in Your Garden, The Wonders I See, The Audubon Book of True Nature Stories, and The Audubon Society Encyclopedia of North American Birds. Terres received an honorary Doctor of Letters from the University of North Carolina (1986), the Merit Award of Art Directors Club of New York and the Silver Medal and Citation from the German Government for the authorship of The Audubon Society Encyclopedia of North American Birds.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, publications, research notes, photographs, and manuscript versions of some of Terres' work.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( 1907-1989 )
Series II: Publications ( 1901-1988 )
Series III: Subject Files ( 1909-1987 )
Series IV: Photographs ( undated )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Natural History. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Natural history.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Photographs.; Negatives.; Financial Records.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated by Mr. Terres.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, 1907-1989
  - Bibliography—Personal, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - B, 1982-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Baldwin, Ian, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Bass, Plato, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Bent, A.C., 1947-1949 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Bird Banding, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Bristol, Barbara “Bobbie”, 1979-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - C, 1963-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Cameron, Angus, 1978-1979 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Carruth, Gorton, 1962-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Cohen, R. Robert, 1976-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - D, 1963-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Der Sarkissian, Michael, 1946, 1981, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - F - G, 1983-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Fisher, A.K., 1907, 1945-1951 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - General, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - H, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Island Beach, 1952-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - J, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - K - M, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Landreth, F. Hobart, 1973-1979 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Nelson, Morley, 1986-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Nye, G. Alva, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Peale, Norman Vincent, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - S, 1979-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Songbirds, 1983-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Sprunt, Alexander, Jr., 1956 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - Stronecker, Marge, 1981-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Stuart, Jesse, 1953-1956 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Swope, Gerard, Jr., 1953-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - T - V, 1983-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Teale, Edwin Way, 1963, 1978, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Terres Family, 1983-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - “Wonders I See”, 1959-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Verner, Jared, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Wetmore, Alexander, 1947 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
- Series II: Publications, 1901-1988
  - Articles Sold, 1945-1947 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Animals “Adopting People”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - “The Big Voice at Muskrat Pond”, 1931-1963, 1983, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - “Birds in Your Garden”, 1901-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - Book Reviews by J.K.T., 1951-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - Book Reviews published, 1948-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
  - Books—Comments and Reports, 1961-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - Buteo Books, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - Copyright Documents, 1962-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - Encyclopedia and Scheer as agent, 1973, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
  - “How Do Birds Find Their Way?”, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - “Old Hoot and her Night Tribe”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - “Rattling Their Tails Behind Them”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 49)
  - Reference material for writing, 1926-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 50)
  - Search for the Golden Mouse, 1966-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 51)
  - “Songbirds”, 1953-1986 (Box 1:, Folder 52)
  - “Swan”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 53)
  - “Swift on the Wing”, 1944-1945, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
  - “Taming of the Shrew”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 55)
  - “Whatever Happened to Baby Bird?”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 56)
  - “What Scientists Say to a Naturalist”, 1967-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 57)
  - “When a Young Bird Says Goodbye”, 1968, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 58)
  - Wilson Bulletin, 1981-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 59)
  - “Wonders I See” Excerpts, undated (Box 1:, Folder 60)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1909-1987
  - Academy of Natural Sciences (Philadelphia), 1934-1935, 1986 (Box 1:, Folder 61)
  - Aggression, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 62)
  - Anecdotes, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 63)
  - Animal Accidents, 1932, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 64)
  - Animal Cooperation, 1923, 1974, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 65)
  - Animal Defenses, 1980-1981, 1983 (Box 1:, Folder 66)
  - Animal Intelligence and Learning, 1969, 1981-83 (Box 1:, Folder 67)
  - Animal Mysteries, 1977-1983 (Box 2:, Folder 68)
  - Animal Pets, 1927, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 69)
  - Animals
    - Ages, running speeds, births in captivity, 1956, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
    - Conflict with Interests of Man, 1954-1955 (Box 2:, Folder 71)
    - Famous Ones, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 72)
    - Homing of, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
    - Humane Treatment of, 1964, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 74)
    - Rare, little known, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 75)
  - Anting, undated (Box 2:, Folder 76)
  - Astronomy, 1980-1983 (Box 2:, Folder 77)
  - At the Sign of the Wolf, 1978-1979, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 78)
  - Attracting animals by sounds, 1941-1953, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 79)
  - Bird attracting, 1982-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 80)
  - Bird drama at Pasadena, 1933, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 81)
  - Bird hitchhikers, 1944, 1983-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 82)
  - Bird Migration, 1974-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 83)
  - Birds
    - Ages, 1964-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 84)
    - Legal Protection, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 85)
    - Songs and Singing, 1935-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 86)
    - Southwest, 1960 (Box 2:, Folder 87)
    - Sunbathing, 1957-1961 (Box 2:, Folder 88)
  - Bluebird, 1981-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 89)
  - Bull's Island, S.C., 1974, 1960-79 (Box 2:, Folder 90)
  - Bumblebee, 1974-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 91)
  - Central Park, notes about, 1958, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 92)
  - Crow Talk, 1923, 1952-84 (Box 2:, Folder 93)
  - Crows, 1927-1985 (Box 2:, Folder 94)
  - Coyote, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 95)
  - Dogs, 1956, 1982-83 (Box 2:, Folder 96)
  - Gray Squirrel, 1920-1967, 1980-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 97)
  - Hibernation, 1951-1979 (Box 2:, Folder 98)
  - Hibernation, 1949-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 99)
  - Mockingbird Studies, 1909, 1922-62 (Box 2:, Folder 100)
  - Mockingbird Studies, 1972-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 101)
  - Nests and Nesting, 1963-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 102)
  - Predation, 1951-1958 (Box 2:, Folder 103)
  - Publicity—Talks, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 104)
  - Reptiles and Amphibians, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 105)
  - Snakes, 1947-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 106)
  - Spiders and Wasps, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 107)
  - Turkey (wild), 1944-1985 (Box 2:, Folder 108)
  - Wildlife Society, 1983-1986 (Box 2:, Folder 109)
  - Woodpecker (Ivory billed), 1960, 1967 (Box 2:, Folder 110)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2:, Folder 111)